Okay בוקר טוב, boker tov, today's דף daf is קנ"ב, kuf nun
bais, 152.
We really are coming
to the winding down here to the conclusion of the מסכת masechet
and we have a nice little אגדתא aggadeta here. Today's entire דף
daf will be a lovely disposition on the infirmities of old age.
So you saw that a little bit yesterday. Well, it's gonna go
on for a while. So now the גמרא gemara says like
this: ביום שיזועו שומרי הבית. bayom sheyize'u shomrei habayit. This is all
an elaboration on פסוקים pesukim in קהלת. Kohelet. On the day that
the guards of the house will tremble, והתעותו vehis'avtu will be bent
down. We'll see. We'll interpret this פסוק pasuk section by section. So
ביום, bayom, this is all referring to the old age. ביום שיזועו
שומרי הבית, bayom sheyize'u shomrei habayit, when the watchmen, the guards of
the house will
tremble, אלו הכסלים והצלעות. elu haksalim veha'atzla'ot. These are like the ribs
and the sides. So you know, your body would start to sag
and they like protect the house because the ribs protect the inner
organs.
והתעותו אנשי החיל vehis'avtu anshei hachayil and the people of valor, the
strong men, will be bent down. אלו שוקיים, elu shokayim, these are
the thighs. ובטלו הטוחנות, ubatlu hatochenot, the grinders will cease. אלו שיניים,
elu shinayim, these are the teeth. וחשכו הרואות בארובות, vachoshchu haro'ot ba'arubot,
and will darken those that see through the skylights. אלו עיניים, elu
einayim, these are the eyes. So all of these parts of the
body will begin to fail. אמר ליה קיסר לרבי יהושע בן חנניה.
Amar lei Keisar le-Rabbi Yehoshua ben Chananya. The Caesar said to רבי
יהושע בן חנניה, Rabbi Yehoshua ben Chananya, מאי טעמא לא אתית לבי
אבידן? mai ta'ama lo asit levei avidan? Why did you not come
to בי אבידן? bei avidan? For those that remember, בי אבידן bei
avidan was mentioned a while ago about like a house of disputation
between... it wasn't clear... רש"י Rashi says between Rabbis and members of
the other Jewish sects. It might have been between philosophers, it's probably
also quite likely. Anyway, or else why is the Caesar getting involved?
Anyway, and different Rabbis, some went because they were... they thought they
could
deal with whatever types of not only intellectual challenges but other challenges
were thrown their way; others were much more reluctant to go. So
he didn't come. So he said to רבי יהושע בן חנניה, Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Chananya, why didn't you come? אמר ליה: amar lei: טור
תלג, tur talag, the mountain is snowy. Which means my hair has
become white. סחרוני גלידין, sachronei glidin, it is surrounded with frost. Which
רש"י Rashi says my beard and mustache are also white. כלבויי לא
נבחין, kalvei lo navchin, the dogs aren't barking. Which means according to
רש"י Rashi that
my speech, you know, I've lost my ability to speak loudly and
clearly. טחנאיי לא טחנין, tachneit lo tachnin, the grinders aren't grinding. So
the teeth don't work either. So he claimed old age, but again
using these very vivid metaphors which exactly ties into what we had
just been saying. בי רב אמרי, bei Rav amri, and בי רב
bei Rav says, here's another like nice whatever or vivid description of
old age: עד דלא אבידנא בחישנא. ad d'lo avidna bacheshna. Something I
haven't lost, I'm looking for. Because people, they get old, they become
bent over, so it looks like they're constantly looking for something that
they lost on the ground, but they haven't lost anything.
Or you mean like he's forgetting and... I don't think so.
I don't think so. תניא, tanya, רבי יוסי בר קיסמא אומר: Rabbi
Yosi bar Kisma omer: טבא תרי מתלתא, tava try me-telasa, two are
better than three. This is like the old riddle of the Sphinx,
right? What is it? Four in the morning, two in the afternoon,
three in the evening or whatever. So two legs are better than
three.
ווי לה לחדא דאזלא ולא אתיא. vai lah lechada d'azla v'lo atya.
Woe to that one that has left and is not returning. מאי
היא? mai hee? What's the one that's left and is not returning?
ינקותא, yankusa, youth. So woe to
the loss of youth. כלילא דורדא... klila d'varda... oh, I'm sorry, I
skipped a line.
כי אתא רב דימי אמר: ki ata Rav Dimi amar: ינקותא, yankusa,
youth, is כלילא דורדא, klila d'varda, is like a crown of roses,
a wreath of roses. סבותא, savusa, old age, כלילא דחילפי, klila d'chilfei,
is like a crown of thorns.
תנא משמיה דרבי מאיר: tana mishmeih d'Rabbi Meir: דוק בככי, dok b'kakhei,
grind or you know, chew with your teeth. דוק dok also is
a phrase that's used to mean like to analyze something closely. But
here it means more the literal meaning of it, like grind with
your teeth. ותשכח בנגרי, vetishkach b'nigrei, and you will find it in
your legs. Which could mean like either which in this context could
mean if you eat well when you're young, it'll stand for you
when you get old.
שנאמר: shene'emar: ונשבע לחם, vnisba lachem, we will be sated with bread,
ונהיה טובים, v'nihye tovim, and we will be good, ורעה לא ראינו,
vera'ah lo rainu, and we did not see evil, which probably means
even in future years we did not see evil. So if you
take care of your diet when you're young, it'll stand for you
in old age.
Or
your teeth.
Oh, it'll stand for you... teeth. It's true, you only got one
set
once you're an adult. Okay, אמר ליה שמואל לרב יהודה. amar lei
Shmuel le-Rav Yehuda. אמר ליה שמואל לרב יהודה, Amar lei Shmuel l’Rav
Yehuda, Shmuel says to Rav Yehuda: שיננא, Shinana, sharp one, שרי כייך,
sharei kayecha, open up your your your sack, means literally your mouth
here is a metaphor, ואייעל לחמך, v’ayyel lachmech, and have the bread
come in, so you know eat well I guess or eat bread
something you know now that you're while you're still young. ארבעין שנין
מיכלא מעלי, Arba’in shanin michla ma’aly, up to
forty until you're forty years old food is good for your health,
מכאן ואילך משתי מעלי, mikan v’eilach mishty ma’aly, and from forty and
onwards drink is good for your health. So what you drink is
is very significant for your health. אמר ליה ההוא גוזאה לרבי יהושע
בן קרחה. Amar lei hahu guza’ah l’Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha. So a
certain גוזאה guza’ah which means a eunuch, but we'll see there's going
to be a play on the word גוזאה, guza’ah, said to Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Korcha, and it appears that this person was also according
to Rashi a some type of a of a heretic, of a
צדוקי, Tzadoki, and he said to Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha, מהכא לקרחינא
כמה? meihacha l’Karchina kama? How far is it from here to Karchina?
And Karchina was obviously a play on the word קרחא Karcha which
meant bald. So he's basically calling him baldy. הוה אמר ליה, havay
so amar lei, so he said back to him, כמהכא לגוזינא, kemeihacha
l’Guzina, the same distance as it is from here to Guzina. And
Guzina, he was a גוזא goza which was a eunuch. So you
call me bald, I'll call you a eunuch. So anyway you know
אמר ליה צדוקי ברחא קרחא בארבעה. amar lei Tzadoki barcha karcha b’arba’ah.
So so the Tzadoki said to him, ברחא קרחא בארבעה, barcha karcha
b’arba’ah, you know a sheared goat is only you know only costs
four זוז. zuz. So they're not worth anything without their hair. So
אמר ליה איקרא שליפא בתמניא, amar lei ikra shalifa b’tamanya, a what
does Rashi say? This is this is also some type of a
of
a castrated Rashi says...
right, ditto, a castrated sheep is goes for eight זוז. zuz. Of
course I don't get it, that's more than a goat. But okay,
maybe it's maybe it's a lower percentage maybe right maybe it's a
lower percentage of how much a sheep normally is.
So somebody spotted the אמר ליה amar lei part. It would have
been all the same, you know, it was a a yeah like
a bald one is
four but yeah castrated one at least is worth eight.
That's a nice point. Where do you see that? I read that
yesterday on Sefaria.
Oh that's a nice sense because that that would make more sense.
He's saying you know at least a bald sheep is worth at
least a castrated sheep is worth more than a bald goat. Right,
because or else why the response back doesn't make too much sense.
All right, anyway חזיא
דלא סיים מסאני. chazyei d’lo siyeim masanei. So so this this eunuch
saw that Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha was not wearing shoes. אמר ליה.
amar lei. Was he poor or was he? I I don't know.
I have a vague recollection of some Gemara that said that he
was poor but I'm not remembering offhand. אמר ליה, amar lei, he
said to him, דעל סוס מלך, d’al sus melech, somebody who rides
on a horse is a king, דעל חמור בן חורין, d’al chamor
ben chorin, somebody who rides on a donkey at least is a
free man, דמנעלי בריגלוהי בר איניש, dimna’aly b’riglohi bar inish, and somebody
who has shoes at least like a human, but if you can't
even have shoes and you have to get around not only not
on animals but on your feet without shoes, that's like well you
know that's subhuman. דלא הא ולא הא דחפיר וקביר טב מיניה, d’lo
ha v’lo ha dachafir v’kavir tav mineih, somebody who doesn't have this
or that who is dug up dug and buried you know dead
and buried is better than him. So maybe that's the maybe that's
the connection here to this general discussion. So אמר ליה, amar lei,
he said to him, גוזא גוזא, guza guza, you know castrated person,
castrated person, תלת אמרת לי, tlat amart li, you told me three
things, תלת שמעת, tlat shamat, hear three things in response. So the
three things probably was the the the castrated sheep and the what
was the first one? How far from here to Karchina and this
last one about what do you call it, about being barefoot. So
you said to me three things, hear the following three things: הדרת
פנים זקן, hadrat panim zakan, a the
the glory of the face is a beard, and obviously he was
castrated here so he did not have a beard. שמחת לב אשה,
simchat lev isha, the joy of a man's heart is a is
his wife, נחלת ה' בנים, nachalat Hashem banim, and the inheritance from
God is children, ברוך המקום שמנעך מכולם, baruch hamakom shemena’acha mikulam, praise
be God that He prevented you from having all three of these.
So these three right just like a nice little exchange of insults.
אמר ליה קרחא מציינא. amar lei karcha metziyana.
So he said to him, you bald person are you are you
in like a you're going to fight? What is it you know
like maybe inappropriate for you as a rabbi whatever anyway so so
you're exchanging insults with me? אמר ליה איקרא שליפא תוכחה. amar lei
ikra shalifa tochecha. He said to him, so a castrated person is
going to give me rebuke? You you're saying I shouldn't fight back,
what are you doing you know rebuking me? All right, that was
an interesting little digression. Not exactly clear what that had to do
with, it does seem petty. Not exactly clear what that had to
do with any of this except that there was maybe something about
being dead and buried, I don't know. Anyway, so now the Gemara
continues. אמר
ליה רבי לרבי שמעון בן חלפתא. amar lei Rabbi l’Rabbi Shimon ben
Chalafta. Rabbi said to Rabbi Shimon ben Chalafta: מפני מה לא הקבלנו
פניך ברגל? mipnei mah lo hikbalnu panecha baregel? Why did we why
did we not welcome you on the
festival? the way my fathers welcomed your fathers, which is a basic
way of saying why didn't you come to visit me on the
רגל regel because a person is supposed to visit his Rebbe on
the רגל, regel, show respect, Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi, he's a נשיא. nasi.
So אמר ליה, amar leh, so remember before it was like why
didn't you go to בית אבידן Beis Avidan and he gave him
some metaphor of being old? So similar type of thing here. סלעים
נעשו גבוהים, slaim naasu gevohim, the rocks have become very high, which
means now you know even the normal types of you know incline
or whatever, right, little obstacles look huge to me now, loom large.
קרובים נעשו רחוקים, krovim naasu rehokim, things that used to be close
are now very distant, right, even short distances now seem like very
long distances. רש"י Rashi also said that people that are maybe it's
also talking about loss of hearing, that now you know people who
are that are next to me and speaking right next to me
it's like they're very far from me. משתים נעשו שלוש, mishtayim naasu
shalosh, from two became three, I have to walk on a cane.
ומשים שלום בבית, umesim shalom babayis, and the one that makes peace
in the house, בטל, batel, is no longer is nullified. So רש"י
Rashi says it actually means his
his sexual desire or his ability to to perform sexually. So what
was he telling him? Well, it's one of the things of old
age. He's just complaining about his old age. You mean it's not
relevant him not not coming? Right, that's true. רש"י Rashi gives another
explanation of what that means. what else did רש"י Rashi say? No,
no, he didn't say another one, but there's other there's some other
explanation that maybe it has to do with digestion or other types
of things.
I would've thought משים שלום בבית mesim shalom babayis you know someone
died in his house.
Yeah, but it it seems no, it seems it's all referring to
some metaphor of old age. So at least the way רש"י Rashi
explains it it has to do with sexual ability. It is interesting
this thing about the the rocks, you know, have become like mountains,
have become very tall. It reminds me of, you know, we just
a few weeks ago did a special week devoted to people with
disabilities at the Yeshiva and one of the speakers, Jason Lieberman, who
actually wrote some beautiful blog posts just recently about being a, you
know, he has
what's it called? Cerebral palsy. Thank you, cerebral palsy, and what it
means, you know, people talk about having kids with cerebral palsy and
he talks about being a father with cerebral palsy. It was very
moving. Anyway, when he was there, you know, he was speaking to
Rabbis about he mentioned he was speaking to a Rabbi once about
issues of access, because it's like everybody you know in theory wants
to do it, but how much are we even aware of, you
know, what the obstacles are? And he said to the Rabbis, he
says if you want to know why, you know, people with physical
disabilities don't come to your synagogue, he says you just have to
walk outside. So he walked outside, he says look, he says there
are fifteen steps there. For me, one step is like, you know,
fifteen steps. So you know and the Rabbi said like, you know,
he never even noticed, you know, how many steps there were. Like
you completely like you know you it's invisible to you until you
become sensitive to it. So that's what he says, you know, the
tiny little things are now like huge mountains. Okay, so now moving
on, second wide line after the two dots, back to a פסוק
pasuk in קהלת. Kohelet. וסגרו דלתים בשוק, vesigru dlasayim bashuk, and the
doors have been closed in the marketplace. אלו נקביו של אדם, elu
nekavav shel adam, these are these are the person's orifices, that they
are no longer like, you know, he's no longer able to probably
go to the bathroom as he used to. ובשפל קול הטחנה, uvshfal
kol hatachana, in the sort of the lowering of the voice, the
falling of the voice of the grinding. בשביל כורכבן שאינו טוחן, bishvil
korkevan she-eino tochen,
why is it that this person is having problems relieving himself? The
first part about the orifices, because of the stomach which no longer
grinds like it should. So that's a different type of grinding than
the teeth. ויקום לקול הציפור, veyakum lekol hatzippur, and rises up to
the sound of a bird. שאפילו ציפור מנערתו משנתו, she-afillu tzippur menaarato
mishnato,
so yeah, a lot of old people have this problem that even
the slightest sound, even the bird, wakes them up from their sleep.
וישחו כל בנות השיר, veyishchu kol bnos hashir,
and all the daughters of song have been laid low. שאפילו קול
שרים ושרות she-afillu kol sharim vesharos or שירים ושירות, shirim vshiros, either
all
the sound of songs or the sound of female and male singers,
דומות עליו כשוכה, domos alav keshucha,
are like something that is like laid low or like a burden,
meaning they they no longer give pleasure. Female and male singers? Yeah,
I know. ואפילו ברזילי הגלעדי ve-afillu Barzillai ha-Giladi אומר, omer, אמר לדוד,
amar le-David, the singing זמירות, zemiros, and even Barzillai the Giladi said
to David, בן שמונים שנה אנכי היום, ben shmonim shana anochi hayom,
I am
eighty years old today. הידע בין טוב לרע, hayada bein tov lera,
do I know anymore between good and evil? Which probably means like,
you know, like like to enjoy life's pleasures as opposed to ethical
judgment. But anyway, we'll see what the גמרא Gemara says. מכאן שדעותיהן
של זקנים משתנות, mikan shedeoseihen shel zekenim mishtanos,
here you see that their intellect changes, but probably means again משתנות,
mishtanos, I don't know if the גמרא Gemara is interpreting this literally
to mean like the lack of intellectual ability, we're actually going to
talk about that in a little bit, as opposed to just like,
you know, the person's sort of ability senses or, you know, the
way that they experience things.
No, no, no,
just in a positive or negative sense. No, no, no, it's more
more sense. אם יטעם עבדך את אשר אוכל. im yitam avdecha es
asher ochal. I may have enjoyed when I was younger I may
not enjoy now?
Yeah, exactly, but I don't think it necessarily means you enjoy other
things, it just means things don't give enjoyment as they used to.
I think that's פשט pshat of the פסוק. pasuk. It's hard to
know whether the גמרא Gemara is referring to this more intellectually, ethically,
or, you know, just in terms of like the sort of appetite
and taste and experientially. אם יטעום עבדך את אשר אוכל, Im yit'am
avdecha et asher ochal, or does your servant, can I even taste
what I'm eating, ואת אשר אשתה, ve'et asher eshteh, and what I'm
drinking? מכאן ששפתותיהם של זקנים מתרפות. Mikan she'siftoteihem shel zekenim mitrapot. מתרפות.
Mitrapot.
Here you see that the lips of the older people are cracked
because he can't even taste what he's drinking. I don't know how
that means necessarily cracked lips. אם אשמע עוד בקול שרים ושרות. Im
eshma od bekol sharim vesharot. Will I ever hear again or enjoy
again the sound of male and female singers? מכאן שאזניהם של זקנים
מתכבדות. Mikan she'ozneihem shel zekenim mitkavdot.
Here you see their ears grow heavy, which, you know, means again
that they lose their hearing or the acuity of their hearing. אמר
רב. Amar Rav. So Rav said, ברזילי הגלעדי שקרא הוה. Barzilai HaGil'adi
shakra hava. He was a liar, Barzilai HaGil'adi. דההיא אמתא דהויא בי
רב. De'hahi amta de'hava bei Rav. Rebbi,
I know that there was a maidservant in the house of Rebbi,
בת תשעים ותרתין שנין, bat tishim vetartin shanin, she was ninety-two years
old, והות טעמא קדרה, vehavat ta'ama kidra, and she was the one
that would taste the pots to determine the spices. So, you know,
there are people that get old and that still have their faculties.
Of course, it doesn't mean that it doesn't that everybody, doesn't mean
that this is not true for many. Anyway, okay, but we got
an ability to say that he was a liar. רבא אמר ברזילי
הגלעדי שטוף בזימה הוה. Rava amar Barzilai HaGil'adi shatuf be'zimah hava. So
again, we are now using this an opportunity to criticize and insult
Barzilai HaGil'adi.
He was good to דוד המלך, David HaMelech, so why are we?
I don't know.
Anyway, ועשית חסד עם בני ברזילי הגלעדי, Ve'asita chesed im bnei Barzilai
HaGil'adi, because they, you know, when he says that to שלמה, Shlomo,
יהיו באוכלי שולחנך, yihyu be'ochlei shulchanecha, he invites Shlomo to do good
to them.
So, you know, this guy was so... Yeah, I think it's I
know. I think it's a little bit more mixed. But anyway, alright.
So he was somebody that was emerged, immersed in, sort of, licentiousness.
וכל השטוף בזימה, Vekol hashatuf be'zimah, and
anybody that's immersed in, you know, sort of licentious behavior,
uncontrolled sexual behavior, זקנה קופצת עליו. zikna kofetzet alav. זקנה, Zikna, thank
you. Old age jumps on him. So meaning, yeah, you know, he
had it worse than most.
We see that he really wasn't
eighty, he was like, you know, well, I don't know, yeah, no,
he was eighty. I don't know, I thought it meant maybe that
they're trying to deal with the fact that it sounds so bad
here, even worse than everything they said before, that they're trying to
say, yeah, he was a special case. You know, Rebbi's maidservant was
was fine, and he was a special case. He had it worse
than other people. תניא רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי אומר. Tanya Rabi Yishmael
b'Rabi Yosi omer. תלמידי חכמים. Talmidei chachamim. Now we get to the
question about intellect. So this actually is a it's an interesting it's
a ברייתא braita because it's actually is a משנה mishnah at the
end of קנים. Kinim.
Didn't we also see it in ברכות, Berachot, didn't we, about that?
Yeah, yeah. It's at the end of so it's so it says
תלמידי חכמים, Talmidei chachamim, Torah sages, כל זמן שמזקינין, kol zman shemazkinin,
the older they get, חכמה נתוספת בהם, chochmah nitvosefet bahem, they get
wiser. כנאמר, Kene'emar, בישישים חכמה, Biyeshishim chochmah, in the elderly is wisdom,
וארך ימים תבונה, ve'orech yamim tevunah, with length of days comes understanding.
ועמי הארץ, Ve'amei ha'aretz, however, you know, sort of the the the
people of the land, you know, the more ignorant people, כל זמן
שמזקינין, kol zman shemazkinin, טיפשות נתוספת בהם, tipshus nitvosefet bahem,
as they get older, you know, they become more stupid, foolish. שנאמר,
Shene'emar, מסיר שפה לנאמנים, Mesir safah lene'emanim,
God removed speech from those that were trustworthy, presumably not meaning trustworthy
in faith, but those that you could normally depend upon in terms
of their speech, וטעם זקנים יקח, veta'am zekenim yikach, and the taste
of of elders he will take, which just sort of echoes what
we said before about losing, you know, taste. גם מגבוה יראו, Gam
migavo'ah yire'u, and even from and even from a height they will
see. What does that mean? Fear, excuse me, fear, excuse me. What
does that mean? שאפילו גבשושית קטנה, She'afilu gavshushit ktana,
even a small little mound, דומה עליו כהרי הרים, domah alav keharerei
harim, looks like the tallest of of mountains. וחחתחתים בדרך, Ve'chatchatim baderech,
and they sort of tremble on the way, בשעה שמהלך בדרך, besha'ah
shemehalech baderech, נעשו לו צווים צווים, nasu lo tzvahim tzvahim,
when they go on the way they become very fearful that they
might trip and fall. וינאץ השקד. Veyanuts hashaked. I'm sorry, so wait,
I think I'm sorry, I
we're back to קהלת. Kohelet. We're back to קהלת. Kohelet. I think
the קהלת Kohelet started from גם מגבוה יראו. Gam migavo'ah yire'u. Yeah,
yeah. Anyway,
so by the way, it's interesting, the פסוק pasuk about that as
they're getting older they become more foolish, doesn't here explicitly talk about
intellect, but somehow to remove the speech, maybe the ability to speak
meaningfully, is what it's understanding. So it's not clear that one is
talking about תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim and one is talking about others,
but רש״י Rashi says if you have a contradiction here in the
פסוקים psukim and one says that as you get older you get
wiser and the other says as you get older you get more,
you know, more foolish, we're going to make the split between תלמידי
חכמים talmidei chachamim and others, assume that's how it falls out. Now
actually besides, you know, just generally obviously חז״ל Chazal favoring the class
of תלמידי חכמים, talmidei chachamim, I actually think that there's, you know,
some truth to this about people, right, right, exercise of mind, right,
actually there's... Actually, didn't you tell me once when we learned this
in קינים Kinnim that you did some study on this? That the
more people have, you know, have exercised their mind, then the as
they get older...
Yeah, there's some evidence from crossword puzzles. Crossword puzzles. Yeah, I actually
have a paper on that. That what? That crossword puzzles are associated
with delayed, delayed onset of Alzheimer's and dementia.
Okay, but that's dementia, but how about just like the ability to
think as sharply as you have as you did in the past?
Actually, that's a debate over whether there's really a significant
loss of faculty
in people who aren't developing dementia. Uh-huh.
You see
this even on young people, you know, the more you develop the
mobility,
right, and the, right, then the more it stays in shape, exactly.
And I think that that, you know, could be a very straightforward
way of understanding the גמרא, Gemara, if you spend your entire your
days, you know, for for decades in intellectual pursuits, you'll become wise,
you know, that faculty will remain much stronger in your old age.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues,
back to the פסוק Pasuk from יחזקאל Yechezkel from קהלת, Kohelet, which
I so which is גם מגבוה יראו, gam migavo'a yira'u, from the
height they will fear, שאפילו גשושית קטנה דומה לו כהרי הרים, she'afilu
gushushit k'tanah domeh lo keharei harim, even a small mound appears like
a tall mountain. וחתחתים בדרך, vechatchatin baderech,
and they're fearful in the way. בשעה שמהלך בדרך נעשו לו תוהין,
besha'ah sheholech baderech na'asu lo tohin, or תוהין, tahin, I don't know
how to read that, anyway when they're going on the way, it
is everything is, it's like a danger, perceived as a danger, they're
afraid they might fall and injure themselves. וינאץ השקד, veyanat hashakad, השקד,
hashaked, thank you,
the
certain tree will blossom, שקדיה, shakediah, right, the almond tree, right, will
blossom. זו קליבוסת, zu klivosos, this is the hip bone, which basically
means that it'll protrude from the, you know, from the body. ויסתבל
החגב, veyistabel hachagav,
and the grasshopper will sort of drag along. אלו עגבות, elu agavos,
so החגב, hachagav, עגבות, agavos, this is the buttocks it'll start sagging.
ותפר
האביונה, vetafer ha'aviyonah, and ותפר vetafer maybe האביונה, ha'aviyonah, and the caper
bush will fail. זו חמדה, zu chemdah, this is sexual desire, that
you lose it. רב כהנא, Rav Kahana, how do
you get that from the word?
I have no idea. חמדה אביונה, chemdah aviyonah, I think some type
of a thing like that. רב כהנא הוה פסיק סידרא קמיה דרב,
Rav Kahana havi pasik sidra kammai derav, רב כהנא Rav Kahana was
sort of learning the פסוקים pesukim in front of רב. Rav. כי
מטא להאי קרא, ki mata lehai kra, when he got to this
פסוק, pasuk, ותפר האביונה, vetafer ha'aviyonah, נגיד ואינח, nagid ve'itnach,
so רב Rav gave a big sigh, oh. So אמר, amar, so
he said, שמע מינה בטלה ליה חמדיה דרב, shma mina bital lei
chemdeh derav, alright so I see that רב Rav has lost his
sexual drive.
Oh, right,
isn't this the רב Rav who had temporary wives when he traveled?
Right, that's a good point, exactly, so that's why he maybe, well,
that's why he really felt its loss. אמר רב כהנא מאי דכתיב,
amar Rav Kahana mai dechtiv, maybe
is kind of תאווה ta'avah is woven into that,
the ת tav from תבטל התאווה, tivatel hata'avah, ותפר האביונה, vetafer ha'aviyonah,
right,
the word
תאווה, ta'avah, desire, the רש"י Rashi
implies, right, חמדת
תשמיש, chemdat tashmish, that's true, like you take the ת tav from
ותפר vetafer and האביונה aviyonah you have תאווה ta'avah or desire.
It's a ת taf not a ט.
tet. ת, Taf, ת, taf, I'm sorry, I don't know where my
head is today. Alright anyway, אמר רב כהנא מאי דכתיב, amar Rav
Kahana mai dechtiv, what's meant by the פסוק pasuk כי הוא אמר
ויהי, ki hu amar vayehi,
God says and it became, זו אשה, zu ishah, this is the
woman. הוא צוה ויעמד, hu tziva vaya'amod, he commanded and it made
it stand, אלו בנים, elu banim, these are children. So, and the
reason, and we're going to see in a minute, we're ascribing it
to God, is basically because it's talking about God putting in people,
men particularly is what it's focusing on, sexual desire, which leads to
them to want to get married and to have kids, like they
have, you know, it's a big thing amongst evolutionary, you know,
biologists about the fact that you know the the men don't, you
know, whatever, would not otherwise invest in marriage if it were not
for if it were not for the sexual drive. תנא, tana, we
find in a ברייתא, Baraita, אשה חמת מלאה צואה, ishah chemat meleia
tzo'ah, good you came just in time רבקה. Rivkah. A woman, I
am sure you are know...
wait, where is this... does this appear anywhere?
No, not that I know of, there's no cross reference. Okay, a
woman is like a a flask filled with, or whatever, you know,
a canteen, a jug, something filled with excrement, and רש"י Rashi says
just means because in our digestive systems, so it basically means, according
to רש"י, Rashi, not specifically women, but just pointing out, I guess
the nature of being human. ופיה מלא דם, upiha malei dam, her
mouth is filled with blood, this refers to the euphemism for menstruation.
והכל רצין
אחריה, ve'hakol ratzin achareha, and nevertheless everybody runs after her. So
that's so negative towards men is it? Well, it's certainly much more
negative towards women, but okay, it's true, I, it is talking about,
you know, the about that the fact that it's the sexual drive
is, without the sexual drive we would not propagate as a species.
So yes...
what did he just say when you say, you know, it's a
flask full of
excrement... not being specific to women, but then the phrase is immediately
suggested
ופי מלא דם u-fi malei dam
with this reference to menstruation. Right, so I don't think, I don't
know about you, רבקה, Rivka, but I'm not buying the apologetics. It's
clearly women.
No, I know, but the question is what does it mean filled
with excrement, why is that specifically about women?
Is it women disgusting? Yeah.
Periods,
maybe it's different kinds of sexual practices?
Oh, you mean כדרכה ושלא כדרכה? ke-darkah ve-she-lo ke-darkah? I was thinking
about that. I was thinking about that.
But the point is, right, if not for השם Hashem being commanding
it then no one would have...
Well, it's not here talking about commanding, it's talking about... חשיבות? chashivut?
Yeah, no, but it means commanded that this would be part of
human nature, the sexual drive and desire.
Otherwise it would be irrational what they're saying.
Exactly. They're saying the need, the desire, right. Exactly.
So although again evolutionary evolutionary
biologist says otherwise there's a desire to settle down and have kids,
men wouldn't invest in marriage and child-rearing were it not for... right.
But the גמרא Gemara here at the end says it's even talking
about the just the power of the sexual desire.
But we just said the desire ends, so then when the desire
ends, the old age, you go back to being the disgusting...
They never they never stop, it's just that men are always running
after them. Right. Right.
The connection is how women as far as he's concerned...
right. I think what I think is fascinating is that
there's no
on the one hand the גמרא Gemara sort of speaks about like
the purpose of the sexual drive is
causes us to want to have sex and therefore want to have
kids, but at the it also juxtaposes it with רב Rav just
sort of mourning its loss even though he's not mourning like the
ability to no longer have kids, so it's almost like very touching
about that is just a reality of human nature without having to
frame it in a specifically in a religious
context. Anyway, so alright so now the גמרא Gemara continues, כי הולך
אדם אל בית עולמו, ki holech adam el beit olamo, because a
person goes to his eternal house. אמר רב יצחק, Amar Rav Yitzchak,
said רב יצחק, Rav Yitzchak, מלמד שכל צדיק וצדיק נותנין לו מדור
לפי כבודו, melamed she-kol tzaddik ve-tzaddik notnin lo mador le-fi kevodo, every
righteous person has their own sort of dwelling place because את האדם
אל בית עולמו et ha-adam el beit olamo in the singular not
like בית עולמים. beit olamim. Everyone gets their particular עולם הבא. Olam
Ha-ba. משל למלך שנכנס הוא ועבדיו
לעיר, mashal le-melech she-nichnas hu ve-avadav le-ir, the story of a king
who goes he and his servants into a city. כשהן נכנסין כולם
בשער אחד נכנסין, keshen nichnasin kulam be-sha'ar echad nichnasin,
when they go in they all go in the same gate, so
everybody goes to עולם הבא Olam Ha-ba they go through the same
gate. וכשהן לנין כל אחד ואחד נותנין לו מדור לפי כבודו, u-keshen
lanin kol echad ve-echad notnin lo mador le-fi kevodo, but when it's
time to go to bed every everybody gets a lodging according to
what is due to them according to their honor. So every so
everybody has their own special place in גן עדן Gan Eden or
עולם הבא. Olam Ha-ba. ואמר רב יצחק, Ve-amar Rav Yitzchak, מאי דכתיב,
mai de-chtiv, what's meant by the פסוק, pasuk, כי הילדות והשחרות הבל,
ki ha-yaldut ve-ha-shachrut havel,
because youth and black hair, youth is meaningless. דברים שאדם עושה בילדותו,
Devarim she-adam oseh be-yalduto, things that you do in your young age,
משחירין פניו לעת זקנתו. mashchirin panav le-et ziknato.
So we're sort of ignoring the הבל, havel, but they blacken your
face when you're older. רש"י Rashi says this refers to again sort
of sexual activity. If the person is overly engaged in sexual activity
when they're young, it'll come back to haunt them when they're old.
In other words you found something to do when you're young
you're embarrassed when you're old.
I understand, רש"י Rashi is explaining it in context of the previous
discussion. ואמר רב יצחק, Ve-amar Rav Yitzchak, קשה רימה למת. kashah rimmah
la-met. Now we get into a fascinating גמרא Gemara which appears elsewhere
as well about the nature of the soul after death. Now that
we're talking about all the failings of old age, now we get
to okay the guy's dead now let's talk about the realities after
death. קשה רימה למת, kashah rimmah la-met, so a
maggot eating away at a dead body is as difficult כמחט בבשר
החי, ke-machat be-vasar ha-chai, like a needle into living flesh, into a
flesh of a live person. So the dead person feels it when
the maggots eat away at his body. Is he feeling it
like... No, let's keep on reading. שנאמר, shene'emar, as the פסוק pasuk
says, אך בשרו עליו יכאב, ach besaro alav yichav, even his flesh
will pain upon him. ואמר רב חסדא, Ve-amar Rav Chisda,
נפשו של אדם מתאבלת עליו כל שבעה, nafsho shel adam mitabelet alav
kol shivah, a person's soul mourns for the person for the entire
week of שבעה. shivah. So the soul is there mourning for the
loss of himself, his body. שנאמר, shene'emar, ונפשו עליו תאבל, ve-nafsho alav
te'avel, and his soul will mourn for him, mourn over him. וכתיב,
u-chtiv, ויעש לאביו אבל שבעת ימים, va-ya'as le-aviv evel shiv'at yamim, and
we know that אבל evel is seven days. אמר רב יהודה, Amar
Rav Yehuda, מת שאין לו מנחמים, met she-ein lo menachamim, now this
ties into the idea that it's not just that the soul is
there and is also sitting שבעה shivah as it were, that a
dead person does not have those to receive תנחומים tanchumim is what
it means, that basically does not have any mourners, so doesn't have
a family, הולכין עשרה בני אדם ויושבין במקומו. holchin asarah benei adam
ve-yoshvin bi-mekomo. Ten people go and sit in the place of where
that person used to live. I mean sometimes you'll hear about that,
that they'll have a מניין minyan in a person's apartment, an old
person who died doesn't have any family, and they'll have a מניין
minyan during שבעה. shiva. So the idea is that somehow the soul
is still sitting שבעה. shiva. It's actually a beautiful idea, you know,
of respect for the dead. Somebody should mourn the loss, and there's
a respecting of the dead even if there's not just about the
relatives. You know, there's a whole discussion about אבילות, avelus, whether certain
practices are כבוד המת kavod hameis or כבוד החי, kavod hachai, whether
they're done for the sake of the mourners or they're done for
the sake of the deceased. So here clearly it's bringing the dead
person himself, him or herself into the, you know, mourning for the
loss of his or her own
body. ההוא דשכיב בשיבבותיה דרב יהודה. Hahu deshachivi beshivuseih d'Rav Yehuda. Somebody
died in the neighborhood of רב יהודה. Rav Yehuda. לא הוו ליה
מנחמים. Lo hav leih menachamim. There were not, again it literally means
people to give consolation, but it really means people to receive consolation.
There were not, there was nobody sitting שבעה. shiva. כל יומא הוה
דבר רב יהודה בעשרה. Kol yoma hava davar Rav Yehuda b'asara. Every
day רב יהודה Rav Yehuda would get ten people. ויתיב בדוכתיה Veyasiv
beduchteih and sit in the place of where this person used to
live. לאחר שבעה ימים, Le'achar shiva yamin, after seven days, אתחזי ליה
בחלמיה דרב יהודה. itchazei leih bechelmeih d'Rav Yehuda. So the deceased appeared
in a dream and a dream of רב יהודה. Rav Yehuda. ואמר
ליה Ve'amar leih and said to him, תנוח דעתך שהנחת את דעתי.
tanuach da'atach shehenachta et da'ati. Your mind should be at ease since
you have set my mind at ease. So thank you for sitting
שבעה shiva for me, that that was, you know, very meaningful for
me as the dead departed. This is a הלכה halacha that you
try to, yeah, bring a מניין. minyan. I mean, I remember as
a young kid once like that somebody died and there was nobody
sit שבעה shiva and we all went and made a מניין minyan
there in the house, you know. But there's again, even you know,
so one is there's sort of metaphysics of the גמרא, Gemara, the
belief about the dead body hovering over, as it were, or sitting
שבעה. shiva. But you know, there's also something I think profound about
the fact that nobody should leave the world without other people, like
experiencing the loss, without it making some type of an impact.
It's a bit more than just sit and have a מניין, minyan,
right? It's not exactly sitting שבעה shiva over his spirit.
Right. Right. Okay, אמר רבי אבהו. amar Rabbi Abahu.
Said רבי אבהו. Rabbi Abahu. כל שאומרין בפני המת Kol she'omrin bifnei
hameis and now we're getting back to also the spirit of the
dead, you know, sort of being hovering over and being aware of
what's happening. כל שאומרין בפני המת. Kol she'omrin bifnei hameis. Anything you
say in the presence of a dead body. יודע. yodeiah. He's, the
person is aware of, you know, עד שיסתם הגולל. ad sheyistom hagolel.
Until you actually, you know, put the cover on the coffin. So
which obviously is important in terms of thinking about like eulogy, right?
Is the eulogy just for the, you know, for those that are
sitting שבעה, shiva, or does it also make the dead person feel
better? כבוד המת? kavod hameis? You know, so when the גמרא Gemara
often discusses כבוד המת kavod hameis there's a question, I think, about
whether it means it has to be built on this metaphysical assumption.
When the גמרא Gemara says certain things that you do are for
the respect of the dead, does it literally mean that the dead
person is aware and is, you know, and is being respected even
now? Or does it mean to show respect for the person who,
you know, for the dead, but not as though there is some,
you know, the soul is still there receiving the respect? The גמרא
Gemara here interprets that to be, you know, very literal, that the
person is still, the soul is still there, he hears the, and
he hears the הספדים. hespeidim. So it's like, you know, what was
it, what was that scene from, was it Tom Sawyer or Huckleberry
Finn where he fakes his own death and he gets to hear
all of him, and he gets to hear all of his הספדים?
hespeidim? So here according to the גמרא Gemara you don't have to
worry, you'll get to hear the הספדים hespeidim anyway. Okay, until they've
closed the coffin. פליגי בה רב חייא ורבי שמעון ברבי. Pligi ba
Rav Chiya veRabbi Shimon berabbi. So there's a debate between רב חייא
Rav Chiya and רבי שמעון ברבי Rabbi Shimon berabbi when the person
stops hearing what's spoken about him. חד אמר עד שיסתם הגולל. Chad
amar ad sheyisatem hagolel. One says until the coffin cover is, the
coffin is sealed. וחד אמר עד שיתאכל הבשר. Vecha amar ad sheyitachel
habasar. Until the flesh is consumed. So, you know, so that's quite
a while. But presumably only בפניו, bifanav, only when you're at the
graveside. מאן דאמר עד שיתאכל הבשר, Man d'amar ad sheyitachel habasar, the
one that says until the flesh is actually consumed, דכתיב: dichtsiv: אך
בשרו עליו יכאב ונפשו עליו תאבל. ach besaro alav yich'av venafsho alav
te'eval. That his flesh will pain him, which we said means when
the maggots are eating away the flesh, and his soul mourns for
him. So the soul is still present as long as the flesh
is being eaten away. מאן דאמר עד שיסתם הגולל, Man d'amar ad
sheyisatem hagolel, the one that says until the coffin is
sealed, דכתיב: dichtsiv: וישוב העפר על הארץ כשהיה והרוח תשוב אל האלהים
אשר נתנה. veyashov he'afar al ha'aretz keshehayah veharuach tashuv el ha'elohim asher
netanah. So as soon as the dust goes back to the earth,
now you could say the dust means that the body is decomposed,
but here it's being understood that the human flesh, the human person
who is made originally from dust, once he is put in the
ground, then the spirit goes back, does not hover around anymore close
to the body.
Is that even before the cover is put on then?
No, it's, oh you mean once it's in the ground even before
the cover? Yeah, okay.
It's still in the ground.
Maybe it's not fully in the ground until it's covered up anyway.
Yeah, okay.
We saw this in ברכות Berachos about how we
know if they can hear. Right. We've some of this, there was
a parallel. Yes, yes, yes. About the two women and being bound
in the reed. Yeah, there's a parallel. Yeah, yes, yes, got the
two women and being buried in the, in the reed. Yeah, there's
a parallel סוגיא, Sugya, but there's stuff here that wasn't in ברכות
Brachot and stuff in ברכות Brachot that wasn't here. Okay. תנו רבנן:
Tanu Rabbanan: והרוח תשוב אל האלהים אשר נתנה, Ve'haruach tashuv el ha'Elohim
asher netanah, the spirit will return to the God who has given
it. תנא, Tana, תנה לו כמו שנתנה לך. Tne lo k'mo she'netanah
lach. So give it back to God the same way God has
given it to you. בטהרה, Betaharah, in purity. So don't soil your
soul during the time you're alive, you have to ensure that you
give it back the way you received it. אף אתה, Af atah,
so
did I skip a line? כמו שנתנה לך בטהרה, K'mo she'netanah lach
betaharah, I just put the comma in the wrong place. The same
way God has given it to you in purity, אף אתה בטהרה,
Af atah betaharah, you give back to God in purity. משל למלך
בשר ודם, Mashal le'melech basar vadam, comparison to a human king, שחלק
בגדי מלכות לעבדיו, She'chalak bigdei malchut le'avadav, he gave, you know, a
kingly garment to his servants. Like the soul is kingly, it's from
God and he gave these to his servants. פקחים שבהן, Pikechim shebahen,
the smart ones, קיפלום והניחום בקופסא, Kiplum vehinichum be'kufsa, folded them up,
put them in a box, protected them, made sure they were pristine.
טיפשים שבהן, Tipshim shebahen, the foolish ones, הלכו ועשו בהן מלאכה, Halchu
ve'asu bahen melacha, they used it when they went out to the
fields and to do their work. לימים, Leyamim, they didn't show it
any respect. ביקש המלך את כליו, Bikesh hamellech et kelav, the king
asked for his garments back. פקחים שבהן החזירו לו כשהן מגוהצים, Pikechim
shebahen hechziru lo keshen meguhatzim, so the smart ones returned them when
they were all like, you know, freshly laundered, when they were when
they were like shining clean. טיפשים שבהן החזירו לו כשהן מלוכלכים, Tipshim
shebahen hechziru lo keshen meluchlachim, the foolish ones gave it back and
they were soiled. שמח המלך לקראת פקחים, Samach hamellech likrat pikechim, he
was very he rejoiced to greet the wise ones, וכעס לקראת טיפשים,
Ve'ka'as likrat tipshim, and he was angry to encounter the foolish ones.
על פקחים אמר, Al pikechim amar, for the wise ones he said,
ינתנו כלי לאוצר, Yinatnu kelai le'otzar, great, so now my, you know,
my garments will be put into the storehouse, you know, so meaning
where they belong. So again the soul gets to go where it
belongs in עולם הבא. Olam Haba. והם ילכו לבתיהם לשלום, Vehem yelchu
levateihem leshalom, and they will go to their house in peace. So,
you know, so that's the צדיקים. Tzadikim. ילכו לבתיהם לשלום. Yelchu levateihem
leshalom. Where was I? ועל
טיפשים אמר, Ve'al tipshim amar, and for the foolish ones he said,
כלי ינתנו לכובס, Kelai yinatnu lechoves, so first of all my garments
have to get laundered. Now who do you think is going to
launder the souls?
גיהנום, Gehennom, right. That will have to purge and cleanse the soul.
והם יתחבשו בבית האסורים, Vehem yitchabshu beveit ha'asurim, and they will be
bound up in the prison. We'll see what that means. אמר הקדוש
ברוך הוא, Amar HaKadosh Baruch Hu, על גופן של צדיקים אומר, Al
gufan shel tzadikim omer, regarding their body it says, interesting chiastic structure
because we were talking about soul and body, you know, now we're
going to reverse it anyway. Regarding their body God says, יבוא שלום
ינוחו על משכבותם, Yavo shalom yanuchu al mishkevotam, that they will come
in peace they'll lie down in their beds. ועל נשמתן הוא אמר,
Ve'al nishmatan hu omer, והיתה נפש אדוני צרורה בצרור החיים, Vehayetah nefesh
adoni tzerurah betzror hachayim, the soul of my master will be bound
up in the bound of life, meaning that it's right there with
God under the כיסא הכבוד Kise HaKavod according to גמרא Gemara which
we'll see in a minute. So their body gets put to rest,
you know, properly and their soul gets goes back to the right
place. על גופן של רשעים, Al gufan shel rasha'im, by the body
of the wicked, הוא אומר, Hu omer, אין שלום אמר השם לרשעים,
Ein shalom amar Hashem lerasha'im, there is no peace says God to
the wicked. It's not exactly clear what that means, that they won't
be buried properly, that their body somehow will decompose, you know, differently
or I don't it's not exactly clear what it means exactly is
going to happen to the bodies. ועל נשמתן הוא אמר, Ve'al nishmatan
hu omer, regarding their souls it says, ואת נפש אויביך יקלענה בתוך
כף הקלע, Ve'et nefesh oyvecha yekale'enah betoch kaf hakela, and the soul
of your enemies you, you know, you should sort of it's like
shoot it like as, as by a what are those things called
that דוד David used? A slingshot. As it was as it would
be shot by the, you know, by the pocket by by like
the, you know, the pocket of a slingshot. Okay, so it should
be shot across the world this soul their soul. תניא רבי אליעזר
אומר, Tanya Rabbi Eliezer omer, נשמתן של צדיקים גנוזות תחת כיסא הכבוד.
Nishmatan shel tzadikim genuzot tachat Kise HaKavod. The so this is again
an elaboration on the previous point. The souls of the righteous are
hidden under God's heavenly chair. שנאמר והיתה נפש אדוני צרורה בצרור החיים.
Shene'emar vehayetah nefesh adoni tzerurah betzror hachayim. ושל רשעים, Veshel rasha'im, and
that of the wicked, זוממות והולכות, Zomemot ve'holchot, or
are like, you know, sort of like are like stretched out over
the world. ומלאך אחד עומד בסוף עולם ומלאך אחד, Umalach echad omed
besof olam umalach echad, I'll read the parentheses, עומד בסוף עולם, Omed
besof olam, one
one angel stands at one side of the world, the other at
the other side, and they play catch with this person's soul. ומקלעין
נשמתן זה לזה, Umekal'in nishmatan zeh lazeh, and they basically slingshot the
souls from one to the other. Okay, they sort of play like
what's that thing with the ball and the paddle? Paddleball. They play
paddleball with your soul. שנאמר ואת נפש אויביך יקלענה בתוך כף הקלע.
Shene'emar ve'et nefesh oyvecha yekale'enah betoch kaf hakela. Okay, אמר ליה רבה
לרב נחמן, Amar lei Rabbah leRav Nachman, סבינא ומאי? Sbeina u'mai? Okay,
how about average people? That's wicked and righteous. What about average people?
אמר ליה, Amar lei, אי כמא דשכיבנא לא אמרי לכו. Ei k'ma
deshchivna lo amri lacho. If I were to have died if I
were to die I would not be able to tell you. Why?
Because I'm not a בינוני. Beinoni. But anyway, האי מילתא, Hai milta,
I couldn't tell you. בר הכי אמר שמואל, Bar hachi amar Shmuel,
here's what שמואל Shmuel says, אלו ואלו לדומה נמסרו. Elu ve'elu leDumah
nimseru. Both the wicked and the average are given over to דומה
Dumah who is is the angel appointed over, you know, over spirits,
over the over the. the souls, הללו יש להם מנוח, Halalu yesh
lahem manoach, some of them have rest, הללו אין להם מנוח, Halalu
ein lahem manoach, the wicked don't have rest. So the only the
righteous, it's actually a quite disturbing גמרא Gemara because it basically says
that only the righteous get,
we normally say צדיקים Tzadikim get עולם הבא. Olam Ha-ba. So and
רשעים Reshaim get גיהנום. Gehennom. So what about the middle so, you
know, the Christians have this belief in what? Purgatory, right? So what
is that? Is that some intermediate stage and what happens? Are you
there forever?
No, it's actually more like our גיהנום. Gehennom.
And then after after a period there you get up to go
to heaven. Anyway, so here it has also like the average people
are not going to heaven, you know, but they are not at
least they are not in this disturbed state. They're just in a
neutral state. What about the wicked are punished, the righteous are rewarded
and the average ones don't go to גיהנום Gehennom or גן עדן,
Gan Eden, they just they're just in a very neutral peaceful state.
It's the angel דומה Duma and רש"י Rashi says that's the name
of...
Yeah, I don't know, I'd have to look about where else it
comes up.
הללויה ולא כל יורדי דומה. Halleluyah v'lo kol yordei Duma. Right.
Doesn't mean that literally but...
Those who go down, right, יורדי דומה, Yordei Duma, right, so like
in literally it means the abyss, right. Right,
the גמרא Gemara here has, oh, you mean how does רש"י Rashi
know it refers to an angel and not to, oh you mean
how you know it means an angel and doesn't mean דומה Duma
like it means in the פסוק, pasuk, which is just like the
netherworld or something like that. Interesting. I don't know. I'd have to
see where else that appears in the גמרא. Gemara.
Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this, אמר רב מרי,
Amar Rav Mari, so said רב מרי, Rav Mari, עתידי צדיקי דהוו
עפרא, Atidi tzaddiki d'havu afra, in the end the righteous will become
dust, דכתיב, dikhsiv, וישוב העפר על הארץ כשהיה, veyashov he-afar al ha-aretz
k'she-hayah, that it will return to the world as it was. Now
what is why is that a חידוש? chidush? Everybody becomes dust. It
might mean that based on the fact that the גמרא Gemara before
said that the צדיקים tzadikim go even their bodies go in are
protected in peace, maybe the גמרא Gemara actually thought that the bodies
of the righteous did not decompose. And now here he is
saying, you know what, they are going to turn to dust. Now
let's keep on
going. הנהו קפולאי, Hanehu kafula'i, there were these grave diggers that were
digging in the land of רב נחמן. Rav Nachman. So, נחר
בהו רב אחא בר יאשיה. nachar behu Rav Acha bar Yoshiya. So
רב אחא בר יאשיה Rav Acha bar Yoshiya who had been buried
there basically rebuked them. So his body somehow was still there, sat
up in the grave or something, he yelled at them and said
what are you guys doing digging in my grave? So, אתו, asu,
so again this goes to the assumption that the righteous people not
only are their souls with God but their bodies are preserved. אתו
ואמרו ליה לרב נחמן, Asu v'amru lei l'Rav Nachman, they came and
said to רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, נחר בן גברא, nachar ban gavra,
a person rebuked us. אתא ואמר ליה, Asa v'amar lei, מאן ניהו
מר? man nihu Mar? So he came and he said to him,
so רב נחמן Rav Nachman came and he said who are you?
אמר ליה, Amar lei, אנא אחא בר יאשיה, ana Acha bar Yoshiya,
I'm אחא בר יאשיה. Acha bar Yoshiya. אמר ליה, Amar lei, ולאו
אמר רב מרי עתידי צדיקי דהוו עפרא? velav amar Rav Mari atidi
tzaddiki d'havu afra? Wait,
I don't get it, how can your body still be around? רב
מרי Rav Mari says that even the righteous will become dust. אמר
ליה, Amar lei, ומני מרי דלא ידענא ליה? u-mani Mari d'lo yadeina
lei? Who's this מרי Mari guy, I never heard of him. So
he wasn't alive when I was alive or whatever, I don't פוסק
pasken like him. אמר ליה, Amar lei, והא קרא כתיב, ve-ha kra
ksiv, but it's a פסוק, pasuk, וישוב העפר על הארץ כשהיה, veyashov
he-afar al ha-aretz k'she-hayah, that the dust will return to the ground
where it came from as it was. אמר ליה, Amar lei, דאקרייך
קהלת לא אקרייך משלי, de-akrayakh Koheles lo akrayakh Mishlei,
the person who read to you קהלת Koheles never taught you משלי,
Mishlei, דכתיב, dikhsiv, ורקב עצמות קנאה, u-rekav atzmos kinah, and
the sort of the
rotting of
bones is jealousy. כל מי שיש לו קנאה בלבו, kol mi she-yesh
lo kinah b'libo, if you have jealousy in your heart, עצמותיו מרקיבים,
atzmosav markivim, then your bones will sort of decompose and rot. כל
שאין לו קנאה בלבו, kol she-ein lo kinah b'libo, if you never
had jealousy, אין עצמותיו מרקיבים, ein atzmosav markivim, your bones don't do
not rot and therefore that's why I was not, my body, not
every person goes back to dust. גששיה, Gasheshiyei, so he touched him.
חזיה דאית ביה מששא, Chazie d'is bei mashasha, he saw this was
not just a dream, that he actually felt something, there was some
real substance there. אמר ליה, Amar lei, ליקום מר לגבי דביתא. leikum
Mar l'gavei d'veisa. So it's interesting at this stage he, maybe because
he was having such an intellectual debate with a dead person, maybe
he finally thought he was hallucinating, but no he felt him and
then he said, okay, why don't you come to my house? אמר
ליה, Amar lei, גלית דעתך דאפילו נביאי לא קרית. galise da'atakh d'afilu
nevi'ei lo kares. You know,
for a moment I thought okay, you learned קהלת, Koheles, you didn't
learn משלי, Mishlei, now I see you didn't even learn נביאים, nevi'im,
דכתיב, dikhsiv, וידעתם כי אני ה' vi-yedatem ki ani Hashem בפתחי את
קברותיכם. bi-fishi es kivroseichem. You will know that I am God when
I open up your graves. So only God, only after the time
of the
resurrection will we leave our grave. So I can sit up and
talk to you, but I can't leave my grave.
And anyway if you look at the side, it quotes the end
of the פסוק, pasuk, it's not just opening the grave... And then
דכתיב dichtiv וידעתם כי אני השם, Viyadata'tem ki ani Hashem, you'll know
that I am God בפתחי את קברותיכם Bifitchi es kivroseichem when I
open up your graves. So only God, only after you know the
time of the resurrection will we leave our graves. So I can
sit up and talk to you but I can't leave my grave,
grave. And anyway if you look at the side of course the
end of the פסוק pasuk is not just opening the grave ובהעלותי
אתכם מקברותיכם עמי Uvehaalosi eschem mikivroseichem ami when I take you out
of your graves. אמר ליה Amar lay ואכתיב Veachsiv כי עפר אתה
ואל עפר תשוב, Ki afar ata veal afar tashuv, what about the
fact that you must go back to dust? Back to that idea?
אמר ליה Amar lay ההיא שעתא אחת קודם תחיית המתים. Hahu sha'ah
achas kodem techiyas hameisim. One second before the resurrection, then we'll turn
to dust, and then God will recompose the dust and resurrect us.
But for now, our bodies are preserved. So here's going back to
this idea that the צדיקים tzadikim God protects not only their souls
but their bodies, which we saw initially with that whole story with
the king. Now we're seeing what the גמרא Gemara had in mind,
that their bodies are preserved and although there's a statement what do
you mean, it decomposes, the גמרא Gemara is trying to reconcile it
by saying it only decomposes a moment before death, a moment...
yes. So this would support that opinion that they may know until
they decompose. Oh, that's a good point. If they're a גוף, guf,
you couldn't have this whole conversation.
It's a good point, if מתים meisim know as long as their
souls decompose. I hadn't put the two together but you're right, if
you combine it with the earlier גמרא, Gemara, it means that the
צדיקים tzadikim are fully aware of everything that's going on. Right, that's
a good
point. Okay, אמר ליה ההוא צדוקי לרבי אבהו. Amar lay hahu tzedoki
l'Rabbi Abbahu. So a certain Sadducee said to Rabbi Abbahu, אמריתו, amrisu,
you say, by the way does the Artscroll or do they have
a different... whenever it says צדוקי tzedoki I always wonder if it's
מין min or something like that. Was it מינא? mina? מינא, Mina,
that's what I figured. Okay, מינא mina to the Steinsaltz. Artscroll also
sometimes has good corrections. Do you have that? It has מינא mina
or צדוקי? tzedoki? Yeah, צדוקי. tzedoki.
Okay, anyway, so again מין min often it's you know, edited, because
מין min means most often a Jewish Christian. So anyway, that מין
min said and Rabbi Abbahu I think had a lot of issues
with מינים, minim, with Jewish Christians, yeah there's a number of interactions
he had with them. So a certain מין min said to Rabbi
Abbahu, אמריתו, amrisu, you say נשמתן של צדיקים גנוזות תחת כסא הכבוד
nishmasan shel tzadikim genuzos tachas kisei hakavod that the souls of צדיקים
tzadikim are hidden under God's heavenly chair. ובעלת אוב היכא אסקיה
לשמואל? Uva'alas ov heicha askiya l'Shmuel? So the ובעלת אוב uva'alas ov
which is basically like Rashi says a בעל אוב, ba'al ov, a
person, and טמיא tamya is of bone, so the necromancer, how did
she rise up Shmuel's soul if their souls are way up in
heaven under God's heavenly chair? So
היכא אסקיה לשמואל? Heicha askiya l'Shmuel? So it says בנגידא, benigida,
in... with witchcraft. So אמר ליה, amar lay, he said back to
him, התם בתוך שנים עשר חודש הוה. Hasam besoch shneim asar chodesh
hava. That was still within twelve months. What does it have to
do with twelve months? דתניא, Detanya, we taught in a ברייתא, Baraisa,
כל שנים עשר חודש גופו קיים ונשמתו עולה ויורדת. Kol shneim asar
chodesh gufo kayam venishmaso ola veyoredes. So for the first twelve months
of a... of a צדיק, tzadik, the body remains preserved and the
soul goes up and down and up and down, so she was
able to still get the soul when it was on his return
trip.
It's somehow still connected to this world?
Yeah exactly, it's somehow still connected to this world and it's starting
to get... it's also connected to the heavenly spheres. ולאחר שנים עשר
חודש, Vela'achar shneim asar chodesh, after twelve months, הגוף בטל, haguf batel,
which is against the idea that the body only decomposes right before
תחיית המתים, techiyas hameisim, ונשמתו עולה venishmaso ola
and the soul goes up. So again the idea that the soul
is connected to the body but you know only but here that
the body starts to decompose after twelve months of a צדיק tzadik
and then the soul is no longer in this world ושוב אינה
יורדת veshuv eina yoredes and then does not come down again, stays
up in heaven and that's where it's under God's heavenly chair and
therefore she was able to bring up Shmuel while he was still
within the first twelve months. Okay, that was a very fascinating discussion
and we will see more of that when we continue tomorrow.